Guide to the Stanford Historical Society Oral History Program Interviews SC0932
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Diversity Project Interviews, 2009-2013; Series 4
  - Kojiro, Dan, 2011 Aug 12
    Ames Research Center Anti-War Protests -- San Francisco Peace March, 1970 Befu, Harumi California -- East Los Angeles -- High Schools Chan, Paul Dong, Nelson Escalante, Jaime Furumoto, Alice Garcia, Ignacio Kojiro, Dan Koski, Raymond Allen Martinez, Louie Nagai, Nelson Stand and Deliver (film) Stanford University -- Anti-War Protests Stanford University -- Asian American Student Alliance Stanford University -- Asian American Student Alliance -- Newsletter Stanford University -- Asian-American Population Stanford University -- Asian-American Population -- Internal Diversity Stanford University -- Asian-American Population -- Origins Panel Stanford University -- Black Student Union Stanford University -- Dating Stanford University -- Diversity -- Admissions Outreach Stanford University -- Diversity -- Demonstrations Stanford University -- Diversity -- Ethnic Associations Stanford University -- Diversity -- Ethnic Associations -- Fundraising Stanford University -- Financial Aid Stanford University -- Freshman Facebook Stanford University -- Housing -- Ethnic Theme Dorms Stanford University -- Housing -- Ethnic Theme Dorms -- Okada
  - Leckie, James O., 2011 Oct 28
    Professor James O. Leckie was closely involved with the Chicano community on Stanford campus. In this interview, he talked about his background, the recruitment and representation of minority faculty, graduate and undergraduate students, as well as their retention. He also discussed the relationship between the Chicano community and other minority communities.
    Professor Leckie has been on the Stanford Environmental Engineering faculty since 1970 and is an environmental chemist interested in the application of chemical principles to the study of pollutants behavior in natural aquatic systems and in engineered processes. His research contributions have been extensive in the areas of adsorption chemistry, human exposure analysis, and membrane science.
    In 2005, he became a member of the National Academy of Engineering, and received the American Society of Civil Engineering Rudolf Hering Medal in 1981. Presently, he is co-Director of the Singapore-Stanford Partnership program in Environmental Engineering & Science, and Director of the Center for Sustainable Development & Global Competitiveness at Stanford University. He is also Appointed Chair Professor in the Department of Environmental Science and Engineering at Tsinghua University.
    Professor Leckie holds a B.S. degree in Civil Engineering from San José State University (1964), and M.S. (1965) and Ph.D. (1970) degrees in Environmental Sciences from Harvard University.
  - Leonard, Jean McCarter, 2011 Jan 7
    The interview was conducted by Katherine Toy, a Stanford Historical Society board member and senior manager at the Stanford Alumni Association.
    Jean McCarter Leonard discusses her time at Stanford with an emphasis on her experience as one of very few African American students on campus. She talks about dorm life, classroom experience and her interaction with then university president, Wallace Sterling.
    Jean McCarter Leonard ’57 is a community volunteer currently living in the Bay Area. She is a consultant to the California State Department of Education and serves on the Alumnae Board of Cap and Gown at Stanford University. She got a bachelor’s degree in social sciences from Stanford and a master’s degree in education from the University of Michigan.
    Jean McCarter Leonard is married for 54 years to her high school sweetheart, Dr. Fred Leonard, and is the proud parent of two sons, Russell ’84 and Gary, graduate of the National University.
  - McNair-Knox, Faye, 2009 Dec 28
  - Nogales, Luis G., 2010 Jan 29
    Luis G. Nogales relates his experience as a student and then a senior staff member at Stanford University from 1966 to 1972 when the university began to embrace racial and ethnic diversity. He begins by sharing his experiences growing up in a Mexican American family in San Joaquin Valley, California, and his experiences at San Diego State University. He then talks about how those experiences shaped him prior to coming to Stanford.
    He continues with his decision to attend Stanford Law School and the opportunities that afforded him to help recruit Mexican American students. While in law school, Nogales was active in various ways to recruit and bring together Mexican American students. After law school, he served as an Assistant to the President of Stanford University for Mexican American Affairs. He talks about his work with MASC (Mexican American Student Confederation) and MEChA (Movimiento Estudiantil Chicano de Aztlán). He also describes his relationships with other organizations and other ethnic groups, particularly with African American student groups, not only at Stanford, but at other universities and colleges. He also mentions issues concerning worker’s rights and race relations within the Catholic Church and the Mormon Church at that time. Finally, he describes the differences between the early days of affirmative action and diversity at Stanford from how it is in more recent years.
    After leaving Stanford in 1972, Nogales continued to be involved with the university in various roles, including serving on the Board of Visitors of the Law School and the Board of Visitors of the Libraries. He was the Founding Chair of the Stanford Center for Public Service and a member of the Board of Trustees. In addition to these experiences, he talks about a recent class action lawsuit against Texaco and how things changed in the country over time regarding diversity and affirmative action.
    Over a period of 30 years, Luis G. Nogales has built a broad and successful record as a senior operating executive and as a private equity fund manager. Moreover, he has enhanced his business acumen and network by serving on the boards of directors of public and private companies. He has served on the investment committees of the board of directors of non-profit institutions with investment portfolios in excess of $75 billion, which include the Ford Foundation, J. Paul Getty Trust, and Stanford University. In addition, Nogales has strong ties to the Hispanic community within the United States and Mexico. Already, his knowledge of and relationships within these population segments have led to significant deal flow for companies with products and services directed to Hispanic consumers, which is the fastest growing population group and purchasing power consumer segment in the country. A summary of the private equity investments in which Nogales has served as the principal investment professional can be found in Section 7 (“Discussion of Past Investments”) of this Memorandum.
    In 1969, Luis G. Nogales started his professional career after graduating from the Stanford Law School where he worked as Special Assistant to the President of Stanford University until 1972. In 1972, Nogales was selected as a White House Fellow and served as Special Assistant to the Secretary of the Interior. This experience provided the opportunity to work on policy formation and implementation at the most senior levels of federal government. After completing his White House Fellowship, Luis Nogales began his private sector career. He has negotiated business and personnel contracts, labor, acquisition and sale agreements, and has worked with local, state and federal government regulators. As president and CEO of Univision, United Press International and Embarcadero Media, Nogales exercised superior leadership in guiding these companies through a variety of economic and life cycle stages (start up, growth, and turn around). During his tenure at these companies, he recruited and built management teams, and changed work forces to address company requirements. In particular, he successfully planned and implemented programs to increase sales and to reduce costs.
    At Univision, the preeminent U.S. Spanish-language television network, Luis G. Nogales led the company’s growth in revenues by over 20% per year for a two-year period, while positioning the company for a successful sale by rationalizing costs and mitigating regulatory issues. At United Press International, which operated in over 60 countries with over 2,000 employees, Nogales led a turnaround that resulted in the company’s first profit in over 20 years. He reorganized the company and executed a successful sale.
    In the private equity arena, as one of the partners in the Lombard/Nogales Radio Fund, Nogales successfully raised, invested and exited approximately $25.6 million in equity investments, generating a gross IRR of approximately 30% to his institutional investors. The fund acquired radio stations under a holding company, Embarcadero Media. Nogales led the acquisition and management of eight radio stations in four separate transactions and participated in the planning and execution of the exit from these properties over a 3½-year period. Of the eight radio stations, he started six new radio operations by reformatting the programming to Spanish language and rebuilding the sales force to address a different market segment. The remaining two stations were maintained in the same format, English language.
    After selling all the assets of Embarcadero Media, Nogales worked as senior advisor to the Deutsche Bank Private Equity Latin America Group. Among his activities there, he led the acquisition of four outdoor media companies in Brazil to form Brazil Midia Exterior (“BME”) at a price of US$72 million. Although the investment was made during a period of decline in the Brazilian economy, the consolidation made BME the largest outdoor advertising company in the country in a fragmented industry and thus a strategic and valuable company. Since BME’s acquisitions, Clear Channel, a U.S.-based media company, has acquired two outdoor media companies in Brazil, confirming BME’s thesis that the Brazil outdoor media market would be attractive to international strategic companies if consolidated. BME is the largest outdoor company in Brazil with strategic assets, making it an attractive acquisition target. Moreover, a media experienced senior management team was brought in to position the company for further growth and consolidation. In addition to the transactional work in Brazil, Nogales participated in facilitating and helping to negotiate a successful exit from an investment in Mexico, Jugos del Valle, a juice production and distribution company.
    For the past 7 years, Luis G. Nogales has served as the Managing Partner of Nogales Investors Management, LLC, the manager of two private equity funds with $345 million of assets under management. Nogales also has invaluable experience serving on the boards of directors of public and private companies. He has chaired committees in audit, finance, personnel and compensation. During the course of his lengthy tenure on corporate boards, Nogales has provided oversight and advice to senior management through economic cycles and company growth stages. Through his operating and board experience, Nogales developed a working knowledge and expertise in the following industry sectors: energy, home building, consumer products, banking, retail, apparel, and media. He is currently on the board of Edison International, KB Home, and Cedars-Sinai Medical Center. His previous board experience includes Arbitron Inc., The J. Paul Getty Trust, the National Association of Investment Companies, Coors, Levi Strauss, Lucky Stores, Bank of California, Kaufman & Broad S.A, the Ford Foundation, Stanford University and the Mayo Clinic Trust.
    Luis G. Nogales’ strong and influential networks in the business, community and public sectors, formed by years of participation and relationship building, is expected to contribute significantly to the success of the Partnership. Luis G. Nogales graduated from San Diego State University and the Stanford University Law School. He speaks fluent Spanish.
  - Ogletree, Charles, 2009 Oct 24
    Charles James Ogletree Jr. went to Stanford in 1971 as a freshman, at a time of great changes in the country and on campus. He was elected as the chairman of the Stanford Black Student Union at the end of his freshman year. As a student, he was active in student politics and concerned with the recruitment and admission of a more diverse body of undergraduates. He later became a trustee of Stanford University and also involved in minority alumni issues.
    Charles James Ogletree, Jr. is the Jesse Climenko Professor of Law at Harvard Law School and the founding and executive director of the Charles Hamilton Houston Institute for Race and Justice at the law school. He has received numerous awards and honors, including being named one of the 100+ Most Influential Black Americans by Ebony Magazine. Professor Ogletree is the author and co-editor of several books, including The Presumption of Guilt: The Arrest of Professor Henry Louis Gates, Jr. (June 2010), When Law Fails: Making Sense of Miscarriages of Justice (2009), From Lynch Mobs to the Killing State: Race and the Death Penalty in America (2006), and All Deliberate Speed: Reflections on the First Half-Century of Brown v. Board of Education (2004). He was a senior advisor to President Barack Obama during his 2008 presidential campaign. Professor Ogletree is a native of Merced, California, where he attended public schools. Professor Ogletree earned an M.A. and B.A. (with distinction) in Political Science from Stanford University, where he was Phi Beta Kappa. He also holds a J.D. from Harvard Law School.
  - Porras, Jerry I., 2011 Oct 4
    This interview with Professor Jerry I. Porras is part of the Oral History Project on Racial and Ethnic Diversity. Professor Porras discussed what happened in Stanford's history to initiate and then to shape the increase in diversity at the university from the 1960s to the present. He began by recounting his youth in El Paso and continued by describing the scholastic and professional trajectory that led him to Stanford. Porras discussed both the admirable and less-than-admirable aspects of the University’s record of diversity outreach. Most of the conversation about diversity issues focused on people -- undergraduate students, graduate students, and faculty -- of Chicano and Latino descent. One idea that emerges is that the character of diversity outreach at Stanford has evolved over time. This interview offers an enlightening window on that evolution.
    Jerry I. Porras is the Lane Professor of Organizational Behavior, Emeritus, since 2001. Professor Porras joined the Stanford faculty in 1972.
    Professor Porras served as a Business School Trust Faculty Fellow as well as a Robert M. and Anne T. Bass Faculty Fellow. He was the Associate Dean of Academic Affairs at the Graduate School of Business from 1991-1994. He also served as the Stanford’s faculty athletics representative to the Pacific-10 Conference and the National Collegiate Athletic Association from 1988 until his retirement. Professor Porras also served as a consultant to Techint, S.A. (Argentina), 1970–71.
    Among the honors he has received are the Brilliante Award from the National Society of Hispanic MBAs, the Silver Apple Award from the Stanford Business School Alumni Association, and the Kanter Medal from the Pacific Graduate School of Psychology. Professor Porras is the author of Stream Analysis: A Powerful Way to Diagnose and Manage Organizational Change (Addison-Wesley, 1987); co-developer of the Stream Analysis Software Package (1999); and coauthor of Built to Last: Successful Habits of Visionary Companies (Harper Business, 1994) and “Building Your Company’s Vision,” Harvard Business Review (1996).
    He has served on several editorial boards including the Journal of Organizational Change Management, Journal of Applied Behavioral Science, Academy of Management Journal, and Academy of Management Review.
    Professor Porras received his BSEE from Texas Western College in 1960, his MBA from Cornell University in 1968, and his PhD from the University of California, Los Angeles in 1974. He worked at General Electric Co., 1964–66; Lockheed Missiles and Space Corp., 1963–64 and in the U.S. Army, 1960–63.
  - Robinson, Norman W., 2011 Feb 3
    This interview was part of the Project on Racial and Ethnic Diversity at Stanford, Phase One: Undergraduate Students, 1968 to 1987. Norman W. Robinson was an Assistant and Associate Dean of Student Affairs during much of this period, responsible for residential education. He speaks knowledgeably about ethnic theme houses, specific incidents during this period (with William Shockley; in Ujamaa House), and reflects on the process of increasing the diversity of the undergraduate student body.
  - Rosenzweig, Robert M., 2009 Jun 10
    This interview is conducted as part of the Stanford Diversity Oral History Project. Robert M. Rosenzweig discussed his role as associate provost during the time of campus unrest in the late 1960s. He recalled his interaction with different diversity student groups on campus, the Study of Education at Stanford (SES), and his work with various colleagues, including Dick Lyman, Bill Wyman and Rixford Snyder, to promote diversity in the undergraduate student body.
    Robert Rosenzweig is a political scientist who came to Stanford in 1962 and served as university associate dean, vice provost, and vice president. He left Stanford in 1983 to become president of the Association of American Universities until 1993.
  - Woodward, Denni, 2011 Apr 15, 28
  - Wyman, Jr., Willard G., 2011-11-14
    Willard Wyman was interviewed as part of the Stanford Historical Society Oral History Project on Racial and Ethnic Diversity in the late 1960s through the 1980s. He was Associate Dean for Student Affairs and Activities, advisor to the Black Student Union, and served on the Committee of Fifteen. Wyman was also special assistant to President Kenneth Pitzer and worked closely with Provost Richard Lyman during that time. His interview focused on the Tresidder Union 1968 “Taking the Mic” incident where black students took over the mic from Lyman during a tribute to Martin Luther King, Jr. and presented ten demands to the university administration.
    Wyman commented that Stanford was ahead of the curve on ethnic diversity and gave Lyman, who became university president after Pitzer, great credit for reforming the university from the inside. He discussed the difference between African American students versus African African students and the difficulties faced by Native Americans and Alaska Native students.
- Faculty and Staff Interviews, 2007-2016; Series 5
  - Abrams, Herbert L., 2015
    Herbert Abrams was an emeritus professor of radiology at the Stanford University School of Medicine, a senior research fellow at Stanford’s Freeman Spogli Institute for International Studies, and a prolific author of books and scholarly articles. He contributed greatly to the Stanford community through his interests in diagnostic radiology and nuclear weapons. In this three-part interview, Abrams discussed his youth in New York, his residency and teaching experience at Stanford’s medical school, and how his interest shifted from radiology to nuclear weapons research and activism.
    Abrams described his childhood in Brooklyn, centering his discussion on his family and his high school years. His family’s love of language seemingly influenced Abrams to pursue an English major and to work for a variety of newspapers and journals at Cornell University, ultimately taking a job after graduation as a newsreel media analyst for the government. Although his interest in Freudian literature prompted Abrams to apply to medical school, once enrolled at SUNY Downstate College of Medicine, he quickly redirected his efforts from psychiatry to radiology.
    Abrams provided valuable details about Stanford’s original medical school in San Francisco. From 1948 until 1959, Abrams served first as a resident and then as a professor at San Francisco General Hospital and Stanford Lane Hospital. Abrams found the experience both challenging and exciting because, due to the small-staff environment, faculty acted as both administrators and clinicians. Abrams also discussed the increasing importance of faculty research efforts after the medical school moved to the Stanford campus in 1959, highlighting developments in biplane imagery, catheter procedures, and radiation effect studies.
    Against the backdrop of his move from Stanford to Harvard, Abrams turned his attention to his longstanding interest in social activism and growing concern regarding nuclear weapons. Although he previously worked with the Physicians for Social Responsibility group, Abrams’ efforts pivoted towards promoting a more international organization called the International Physicians for the Prevention of Nuclear War. This group studied all matters related to nuclear weapons, worked to raise awareness, and educated Congress about the effects of nuclear war.
    Abrams went on to discuss his return to Stanford in 1985 and his continued shift from a focus on diagnostic radiology to nuclear weapons research and activism. Increasingly, Abrams spent time at Stanford’s Center for International Security and Cooperation studying the effects of nuclear weapons exposure and the intersection of weapons access and mental health. In conclusion, Abrams addressed the need to educate the public about present-day nuclear threats and discussed the various leisure interests he pursued in this post-retirement period.
  - Adams, James L., 2010 Mar 10
  - Amemiya, Takeshi, 2017
    In this oral history from 2017, the noted econometrician Takeshi Amemiya, Edward Ames Edmonds Professor of Economics, Emeritus, describes his early life in wartime Japan, his education in economics, and his years on the faculty of the Department of Economics at Stanford University. His wife, Yoshiko Miyaki Amemiya, briefly describes meeting Amemiya in Japan and her experience of life at Stanford.
    Amemiya begins by describing how Advanced Econometrics, a comprehensive text that is still in print three decades after its initial publication in 1985, evolved from material he used to teach the subject when he first came to Stanford in 1964. About that time, Amemiya explains, microdata on individual households and companies began to become available. Amemiya developed the statistical methods to analyze such data, and he was the first to write a textbook on the subject.
    Elaborating on his early years at Stanford, Amemiya explains that the faculty of the Department of Economics were assigned to different campus buildings, depending on their interests. He says this tended to deter collaboration until the department was consolidated at Encina Hall in the 1970s.
    Amemiya jumps ahead to discuss his later interests: sharing his delight in discovering the similarities of Greek and Japanese customs, including the gods they worshipped and their shrines to the dead. In addition, after traveling in China, he began to write poetry in Chinese.
    Turning to his childhood, Amemiya says he was only seven at the outbreak of World War II, which found his family in Lima, Peru, where his father worked as an executive for a Japanese shipping line. He describes being caught up in an exchange of Japanese and U.S. citizens living abroad at the outbreak of war. Although he was evacuated from Tokyo during the war, he experienced air raids in the area near Mount Fuji to which he had been sent.